Like for example, so when it comes to
precepts, you know, whether something is
you know, whether something is
whether something is under allowance or
not. Yes, you have the you know, the broad
Yes, you have the you know, the broad
definition.
You could you could um
take it in a even more specific manner.
Say like
uh well, like the precept for
entertainment or similar. So, it's like,
"Oh, I I shouldn't watch news." Or you
can say, "Well, that's not necessarily
specified. I could watch news."
Um and that's pretty much what
differentiates whether you're just
keeping the precepts or are you trying
to train your mind through the precepts?
So, it's not to say that watching the news
it's not to say that watching the news
is always bad or always against the
precepts, but it's to say that uh you
can't use an external definition,
however specific, developed, accurate as
a measure for the intentions that come
from your own mind, which is what should
be our reference point.
So, it's like
um
keeping the five precepts, keeping the
eight precepts, and then say, "I'm not
watching the news cuz I take that to
mean the precept against entertainment."
That's fine, but it still might not
necessarily mean you're training your
mind rightly.
You just added more observances to the
precept. So, it's like um that doesn't mean you
So, it's like um that doesn't mean you
should go and watch the news, but it
means basically you need to recognize
that the sole purpose of precept broadly
defined, more specifically defined,
adding more observances to the precepts,
all of that should be serving the same
purpose of uh
of uh
discerning your own intentions.
As a reference point. So, that becomes
the guiding criteria whether you should
watch the news or not. It's like, "Why?
Like what's my current right now,
this living motivation to
check the news?"
There might be some, I don't know,
practical reason and intention rooted in
that reason that's not necessarily
coming out of, you know, entertainment
and distraction.
Um or it might not be. And that's what
you you always That the whole point is
to be to to to kind of direct you to
towards revealing that. Everybody knows
their intentions. It's more like whether
they have trained enough to just admit
to themselves what those intentions are.
Uh intentions cannot be um intentions
cannot be unconscious.
Cannot be like hidden in plain sight or
something because they are the guiding
principle for your action whether you
admit it, whether person recognizes it
or not, they are the the the force
behind any any action, any comma,
anything that you're committing to.
So, it's not a question of
revealing the mystery of where my
intentions are and whether I can see
them or not. It's just sitting down with
yourself and and like admitting, "Hold
on. Why?" Just asking a question.
Why do I watch Why do I want to like say
watch the news or read the newspapers?
Right here, right now. Not yesterday,
not tomorrow, not because, "Well, you
know, the world is in No, no, no. Right
now, where is my my How do I feel in
regard to that?" Where Is there a
pressure? Is there What What feeling is
guiding my need
to to go and watch the news?
Is it like they said like some genuine
whatever reason
for finding out what's happening or is
it like, "Well,
I feel like I I should allow myself."
Well, you know, why? So, those ambiguous
kind of ideas and stuff, that's the
whole point. To bring them up and then
keep pushing with questioning until it's
clear why things are done the way you
want them to do.
The you the way you want to to do them.
Um so so that's why it's like
there's only so far you can go with like
taking the precepts,
adding extra observances,
confessing them, all of that.
If
you're not using that
for this type of like self-drilling
that's kind of taking you in direction
of knowing your own intentions and then
that gradually uh becoming um uh an
emphasized criteria for whether I should
do something or not.
Because obviously the more questioning
you invest in it, the clearer it
becomes. Um the more kind of obvious your
Um the more kind of obvious your
intentions and and motivating factors um
will eventually um be be be seen and
understood. And then you wouldn't even
have to sit through like
um
detailed or profound or elaborate
self-questioning to uncover it because
right from the start you recognize the
state of mind for what it is and you
know what intention is is coming out of
it. And you already know whether you should
And you already know whether you should
follow it or not. And you know if you
follow it, it's going against the
training. Or if you follow it, it's not going
Or if you follow it, it's not going
against the training. You would know
because training is determined by um
the uh uh um
the states of mind that are free from
greed, free from aversion, free from
distraction, free from hindrances.
And and so that's the whole point.
That's the whole point of of training in
precepts is revealing that. So it's not
going to be like
it's not going to be
you know, black and white, clear-cut
like oh, this is a not in the beginning
at least.
So
you might have a reason,
practical need to check the news,
which will be mixed with
you know, the old habits of really
really being into news and geopolitics
or whatever. And
that sense will come up, that habit will
pressure you and stuff. But again, if
you have to engage to to to a practical
extent, you engage only to the practical
extent. And then you contain that pressure, that
And then you contain that pressure, that
need. Cuz you can't help, like you can't
help but but
um
experience the elation, the pressure,
the excitement of that mind that's still
not fully trained.
But you can contain it.
Because like, you know, there's like
this it's kind of similar principle when
when the Buddha on on his deathbed when
Ananda Venerable Ananda was asking
different things to him
saying um you know, what should we do in
regard to this, what should we do in
regard to this. So, what should we do in
regard to women
like as monks? He's like, well
um don't don't look at them.
It's like, well, what if we have to look
at them? Well, then don't don't talk to
them. What if I have to talk to them?
Well, then be mindful and guard your
senses. And it's exactly same principle.
And it's exactly same principle.
So, don't look at anything if you don't
have to. Don't distract yourself if you
don't have to cuz you're just creating
more work for yourself later.
But you can't always avoid it.
So, then you recognize okay, when I have
to, well, then I do it only to this
extent. Oh, but what if like I have to do it
Oh, but what if like I have to do it
longer and my mind will really get all
kind of
excited about it and all habits and
patterns will come up? Well, then be
extremely mindful of that and contain it
and just just make sure you you like do
not lose the end in sight as in
okay, yeah, my mind is excited. I need
to see this through, but the moment I
do, we're stopping this.
So, you are still in control, so to
speak. Like yes, the animal got excited. You
Like yes, the animal got excited. You
can't just force them force it to calm
down, but you can make sure you don't
let it out. You could still keep it in
the same
in the same container. So, as I said,
like you know, things things are not going to
you know, things things are not going to
be black and white. It's going to take a
quite a decent amount of practice before
like the clarity is really like sort of
the clarity is really like sort of
you know, you always know this is
unwholesome, you always know, but until
then the animal will pressure you, the habits
the animal will pressure you, the habits
will come up. So, there can be like as I
said like so there's a factual need to say
like so there's a factual need to say
something.
But the mind is angry. Okay, can you not
say it? If that is a viable option,
don't say it.
But again, living in a in a in a lay
world in particular, you you
Well, you you will rarely have that
privilege to like, "Oh, I completely not say it
to like, "Oh, I completely not say it
and I'll say it later." So, you you have
to say it to some extent. Well, you make
sure you don't like use the abusive
words. Obviously, you know, you not like
a coarse phones.
Um
but you can't help but have the mind
that's already kind of wound up or
something. And there's only now the window of
And there's only now the window of
opportunity to say it and
it's like in that case, the most
important thing is to not lose that
sight of the whole picture.
To not justify speaking out of anger.
Um and to remain aware, okay, I'm saying
this, the mind is angry, but I am aware
of the difference between me saying this
mindfully with the angry mind that I'm not letting
with the angry mind that I'm not letting
it sort of express itself fully the way
it wants.
Yeah, it's not ideal.
But like I said, that's you know
it's not impossible to train even within
that environment.
Like it's a lot it's a lot harder, it's
a lot stickier, it's a lot more gray
areas. That's why the Buddha referred to
the household life as crowded and dusty.
Dirty and crowded and you can't really
it will take a lot of effort just to
kind of get to
manage things rightly, let alone start
uprooting them.
But that's the principle behind. Like
the mind can be mind can be wound up.
Same, whether it's anger, whether it's
lust, whether it's any other hindrance.
And the first and foremost, it's that
what I say like endure it on the right
level, which is another way of
containing it.
And when things are contained
even if you have to do something, if
it's unavoidable as I say like, you
know, to look at the news or to say
something and so on,
it's not the same as if you justified
the action almost beforehand when you
ignore the state of your mind and then
just do it cuz that's how you feel like
it. So, containing it, even if you have to
So, containing it, even if you have to
engage to some extent,
as as that as that simile as that uh
example the Buddha gave, well, if you
have to look uh don't talk, if you have
to talk, well, then be mindful
until the event passes.
You can literally apply that to in
regard to any hindrance, especially in
the world when when when things are
bombarded when things are like bombarded
at you and so on.
So, it's like you don't have to like,
oh, I mustn't even feel this
this this this this kind of
irritation. It's like you can't help
that. Animal is irritated.
So, it's like
it's better to recognize that and don't
sort of think that I must prevent this
from happening.
It's more like, no, no, no, I must
prevent anything on top of it that would
be my doing.
And anything on top of it that would be
your doing comes always
as a result of a single factor, which is
not containing the animal, not
containing whatever whatever you have
felt. Let it it spill out, ignoring it,
choosing to deal with it later.
I'll do it this now and then I'll
confess and I'll do this and and so on
and justifying it like that.
But if you don't do that, you could
actually train even with animal coming
up daily
with stuff. In as a matter of fact,
you'll probably be having quite a lot of
um good material for training.
If the right attitude can be maintained,
the mind will be just coming up with
stuff, but the context remains unchanged cuz
but the context remains unchanged cuz
obviously the person has developed
enough clarity, understood the the the
purpose of the container,
the the knowledge of its own intentions
and recognizing that's the gateway.
Cuz if people don't see that, then they
pretty much overdo and underdo
uh
any any attempt at practice. So, it's
like the mind comes up with the
agitation and they try to get rid of that. They
and they try to get rid of that. They
try to like like like um
choke it, kill it, get rid of it, change
it cuz that's bad.
And then, obviously, that will fail
cuz you overlooked what the gateway is.
Then you have the other ways like on
another occasion the mind comes up and
then they just like
give up. Oh,
I'll deal with this later. I don't care.
But it's like, no, you could find the
middle ground.
Recognize and accept that there's going
to be daily instances, especially
[clears throat] living in LA world,
of your mind coming up at you to let it
out. To let it out, to say, to do things, to
To let it out, to say, to do things, to
look at things, to to engage with
things, and that must have That That
must never be allowed unmindfully.
And initially, it feels like, oh, I must
all the time watch it, but it's like But
yeah, that actually it is easier
than having to fight it.
Thinking that you must change the mind
of anger into something else.
No, you just need to contain it and
don't let it express itself until it
comes down.
That's the message you want to convey.
You need You think you need to You need
to like tackle the mind of lust and
change it and force it to become
different. It's like, no, that's already failing to
It's like, no, that's already failing to
recognize
like what a uh
efficient communication with with the
animal is.
Like, you think you're trying to get it
to not be lustful, not be angry, but
that's not the message the animal will
be getting.
In other words, basically,
it's going to have the opposite effect.
It's going to have like the effects of
suppression, trying to get rid of it,
this and this, which just again, is just
going to going to make them uh the mind,
the animal even more editable, so to
speak, even more prone to those things.
Cuz now you're super sensitive about
anything that can trigger it, cuz you
still don't know where the problem or
solution is.
And it is on the level of containing it.
It comes up, you contain it, and there
will be a pressure to Oh, it would be
nice if the animal is not this way.
If I could change that, then I wouldn't
even have to contain it. Wouldn't that
be wonderful?
And that's the animal tricking you into
opening the door and engaging with it.
Yeah, things will stop coming eventually
if the mind is tamed, but not the way a
person thinks that will happen, which
is, you know, the only way they can
think that happening is through their own
that happening is through their own
desire, through their own ideas of how
it would be nice if the mind doesn't
doesn't come up and then there's a
All of that means it's still falling for
the same type of craving, because of
which it won't happen.
For as long as the mind is not free from
craving, it won't happen. The calming
down of the mind won't happen.
Doesn't matter how hard you concentrate,
how hard you avoid, how hard you protect
your environment, how purely you keep
your precepts, how diligently you
confess your offenses, it's not going to
happen, cuz the craving is still
self-perpetuating inside of that animal.
Having the mind that's angry or
irritated and then having to act
with that state of mind,
uh
the actual the main
confining aspect of that experience
is not the fact that the mind is angry,
it's not the fact that you have to act,
it's the fact that you still do not
clearly understand the line
the line
between the two.
The line between the state of mind, the
extent of the mind, extent of the
pressure, and your choice to act.
and your choice to act.
That's still not seen. So, there's the
sense of confinement from oh, this
experience is coming, the mind is all
wound up, and I have to say and it's
like overwhelming, comes from actually
still kind of implicitly thinking that
the whole thing is a problem.
That the mind is a problem and I don't
know, it's like
so
that's unavoidable. It's going to feel
like that in the beginning, but my point
is
if you if you practice like um
uh uncovering of your intentions through
the right questioning on the base of
precept and training in the the values
of precepts, body, speech, and mind,
mentally, all of that,
uh the line becomes clearer and clearer.
So, you could have the most violently
imaginable state of mind come up,
and it still won't be confining you.
It still won't be overwhelming you.
It's still contained cuz you fully
understood the extent, the range of the
animal. Cuz that range was not understood when
Cuz that range was not understood when
things were were intentions were not
known, when uh when actions were coming
out of ignorant intentions,
uh unwholesome intentions, craving, and
so on.
But once that has been trained away
from, so to speak, or trained out of
you, uh the mind can still come up,
uh the mind can still come up,
but at no point will there be any
confusion about
about
the gateway, the the doorway that I talk
about, and whether you whether the
animal can open it by itself or you are
responsible for it. And once you know
that difference,
then as I said, the most
as I said, the most
state of mind, it will be equally
contained, and there will be no
trembling >> [gasps]
>> [gasps]
>> oh, maybe I'll be locked out now
automatically. It's like there is no
such thing.
It always has to come through choice,
and that has been fully understood.
So then, doesn't matter the pressure,
doesn't matter the state of mind,
doesn't matter the circumstances,
at that point, nothing can make you feel
as confined and overwhelmed and buried
uh how you used to when things were not
clear. And while things back back in the day
And while things back back in the day
when things were not clear I said that
confinement was usually attributed to
the state of mind, to the state of the
Well, imagine like you have a you have a
wild dog that you never met. You'd never
experienced a wild angry dog barking at
you and you just freeze
and you don't know
Actually, snakes snakes are a better
example of that.
Like most people have irrational fear of
most people have irrational fear of
snakes
cuz obviously they
they never experienced or
learned their behavior.
So, the idea is like like I remember in
Sri Lanka it was generally like if you
see a snake anywhere, doesn't matter how
far from you
people would just kind of freeze in fear
cuz they would have the sense that if I
do the slightest small thing wrong, that
snake from like 20 m away, that cobra
that I just saw will come after me.
So, everything then becomes a problem
cuz you don't really understand where
the actual problem is.
And people would generally just freeze.
Just like be overwhelmed, frozen in fear
because they think whatever I'm to do or
not do, doing is a problem, not doing is
a problem. Should I run? Should I stay?
All of that.
That snake from all the way there can
come and bite me and that's the end of
my life.
But then obviously you get to see it.
You get to and there was actually no,
that's that's not how the snake thinks.
That's not how it works. That's not how
its own kind of uh
like physical abilities are. Like it
just it's you realize oh, that's that's
inconceivable. And now, okay, you see a snake. There is
And now, okay, you see a snake. There is
some concern, but you know the range.
You know the extent.
You know what you shouldn't do. I
shouldn't go near it. I shouldn't go and
corner it. I shouldn't go and try and
grab it or things like that. But if I
don't do any of those things, if I
abstain from doing those things, I'm
safe. Even if it comes right by me. It
won't do anything to me.
And once that knowledge is really like
verified, you will be unable to be frozen in fear.
you will be unable to be frozen in fear.
And same happens with the mind. So, when
the mind comes up with these states,
like person becomes aware of it cuz you
know, many people wouldn't even be aware
of it. They would just act out. But
person becomes aware of it, but they
don't know the range, they don't know
any the extent, they don't know where
their responsibility begins and where
the animal is. So then everything feels
confining, everything feels unpleasant,
everything feels like a problem.
Um
only because
well, there is still like lack of
understanding in regard to the nature of
that relationship to put it that way.
So, that's why again the precepts all it
has to come first cuz
doesn't matter how overwhelmed the
person is, it will prevent you from
going too far out in the wrong way that
would genuinely aggravate the cobra, the
animal. So,
So,
you stop doing that for a while, you
endure the pressure on the right level,
you contain it and then exactly like oh,
there's a cobra, I'm frozen.
You do it once, twice, five times, but
it is oh,
it's still actually haven't attacked me.
I mean, okay. Well, maybe I could just
relax a bit. It's hissing, it's
threatening, but
you naturally relax.
When you see that okay, okay. Okay. And
then you become cautious.
Okay, maybe okay now, okay now it's
getting more. Okay, I won't do that. Oh
look, now it doesn't mind this. And it's
exactly the same.
So, you contain the mind and it's going
to come at you because you contained it.
And it's like so but you try to kill it
now, get rid of the whole thing. Oh, if
only I could just drop a bomb and
get rid of that snake. Everything would
be perfect. It's like yeah, not how
things work."
So, the mind comes up. It's like, "Okay,
I recognize it." It would be nice. It
wouldn't be nice that the
I don't even experience it. Yeah, but
that's not up to you.
So, it's like the sooner you give up
those naive expectations of if only I
can concentrate hard enough or do
something magical so the mind will never
come up, the sooner the better.
You give them up, you're closer to train
rightly. It's like, "No.
This is a lifelong task.
As it always was, by the way, even for
people that don't want to train.
There was always a lifelong task putting
up with your mind, following, being
dragged by it, experiencing results of
your actions on account of the pressures
that come from the mind, paying the
price, and all of that.
So, the sooner you accept that it's
actually something that it's worth
invest worth investing effort in, the
better. Like, the less the less damage and less
Like, the less the less damage and less
work you'll have to undo later.
So, the whole sense of confinement, the
whole sense of fear simply comes from
insufficient understanding of "Well, it doesn't
understanding of "Well, it doesn't
matter how close this animal comes."
The the threat
the the the the the seeming imminent danger
the the the the seeming imminent danger
you understood where the line for that
is. The line is only if I act out. The
line is only if I open the gate.
Otherwise, it can't do anything to me.
And once you know that and start
sticking to it on that right level, like
not giving it up, that's when the animal
realizes, "Oh, crap. He knows it."
And then it stops threatening.
Cuz the threats work when you don't know
that it's just a threat.
Then And then, look, it worked. I scared
you. You did it. You opened the gate for
me. Thank you.
But, I scared him. Nope. Nope. Nope.
Nope. And then he's like, "Oh, okay. So,
seems that he figured out. He's not
opening the gate doesn't matter how much
I threaten."
In other words, he's not losing the
container. He's not giving it up
willingly through choice. And that's my
point. You can't accidentally
just lose the container. You can you can
be distracted. You can you can be you
can drift away. All of that.
But whenever the self-awareness
reappears, when you become aware of the state of
when you become aware of the state of
the mind and the state you're in,
there and then the choice you make
determines whether you are opening the
gate and releasing the container or
you're maintaining it in regard to the
animal. So you could be
So you could be
distracted as I said, mindless engaged.
You have to really
focus on this or that task and
at any point through that when
self-awareness comes up, which it will
have to,
that's when you recognize, oh the
container as like, do you then when you
recognize, when you become self-aware of
the container, the state of mind and
your actions, do you then, oh that's
okay, I'll carry on.
Or do you say like, oh oh, I must
protect this.
That's the crucial point. Not like, I
must never be distracted. I must never
drift off. That's impossible.
But it's when the choice is presented,
do you make the right one?